<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<content>
  <rules>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14606</url>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <body>
          
            The Rules of Golf ("the Rules") specify the equipment which may be used to play thegame. These specifications can be found in Rule 4 and Appendix II for golf clubs and Rule 5 and Appendix III for golf balls. In general, they are "descriptive" and "restrictive" in nature - defining what golf equipment should look like and limiting how golf equipment can perform.  
          
          The main objective of Rules 4 and 5 and Appendices II and III is to ensure that technological advances in the design and manufacture of golf equipment are in the best interests of the game of golf.
          While not wishing to stifle innovation, the purpose of the equipment Rules is to protect the traditions of the game, to prevent an over-reliance on technological advances rather than on practice and skill, and to preserve skill differentials throughout the game. 
          The USGA's Equipment Standards Committee ("the Committee") is responsible for interpreting and applying the Rules relevant to clubs, balls and other equipment, as well as determining and advising their conformance to the Rules. The Committee is also responsible for recommending modifications to these Rules, if and when changes are believed to be necessary. 
          The USGA achieves consistency in the decision-making process by maintaining a database of all previous decisions. Additionally, over time, the Committee has developed a comprehensive set of "guidelines" based on these decisions to help consistently interpret the equipment Rules.
          The purpose of this publication is to provide guidelines to manufacturers, rules officials and other interested parties in an effort to assist them in interpreting and applying the Rules on golf clubs and balls. The purpose of the "Field Procedures" section is to offer advice on the procedure an official should follow when faced with an equipment ruling immediately before or during a competition.
          Many of the Rules with respect to clubs and balls can be technical and complex in nature. However, almost without exception, the equipment Rules become understandable after a brief explanation, or with the aid of a simple diagram. Whenever possible, this Guide will attempt to explain the background of a rule and the objective behind it. Also, where practical, the Guide will offer advice as to how best to carry out any certain measurements.
          Please note that this Guide should be read in conjunction with the 2012-2015 edition of "The Rules of Golf." 
          In the event of any doubt over the conformity of a club or ball, the Rules of Golf take precedence. 
        </body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14607</url>
      <title>Field Procedures</title>
      <body>
  
    
    Field Procedures
  
  
    GUIDANCE TO RULES OFFICIALS CONCERNING QUESTIONS ON THE CONFORMITY OF CLUBS AT COMPETITIONS 
  
    
      
        
          
            
            
            Introduction
          
          It is the player's responsibility to ensure that his clubs conform with the Rules. If in doubt, he should not carry any questionable club. However, such guidance is not always appropriate, particularly when a question arises during or after a competition, in which case a decision is required.
          Notes on Terminology Used
          
            "USGA Decision" is one which already exists in the USGA Equipment Standards database or "Decisions on the Rules of Golf" at the time the question arises, though it may be unknown to the player or official concerned.
            "USGA Ruling" is one that the USGA Equipment Standards Committee or its authorized sub-Committee may make on the club which is the subject of the inquiry. It is made after the inquiry has been communicated to the appropriate Equipment Standards representative, whether before, during or after the competition.
            "Duration of Competition Answer" is made by an official involved in running a stroke play competition and has no standing after the competition has closed. The player may use the club for the remainder of the competition. Duration of Competition Answers have no standing beyond the end of the competition and, therefore, the player should be advised to submit the club to the USGA for a formal ruling as soon as possible. The player should also be made aware that any subsequent ruling may be different from the Duration of Competition Answer which was given.
            "Duration of Round Answer" is usually made by an official involved in running a match-play competition and has no standing after the player has completed that round. Duration of Round Answers have no standing beyond the end of the round and, therefore, the player should be advised to obtain a formal ruling or subsequent Duration of Round Answer from the official prior to the next round. Thereafter, the player should submit the club to the USGA for a formal ruling as soon as possible. The player should also be made aware that any subsequent ruling may be different from the Duration of Round Answer(s) given.
          
          
            A. Questions Arising Before the Competition Begins
          
          
            Officials should always ascertain why the player, fellow-competitor, opponent or third party is questioning the club.
            A positive ruling should only be given at this stage if the official is absolutely certain he is correct. As a precautionary measure, always refer to the Rules of Golf and this Guide prior to giving the ruling.
            If the official is not certain of the ruling, and time permits, help and guidance should be sought from the USGA. First, it should be determined whether the club has ever been formally submitted to the USGA for a decision.
            If a USGA Decision exists, and the official finds out in time, the player should be informed accordingly.
            If a USGA Decision does not exist, the official should provide the USGA with a detailed description of the club. If time permits and it is feasible, an e-mailed image or faxed drawing should be sent. The USGA will then offer as much guidance as possible based on the information given and, in most cases, offer a recommended ruling.
            The official should make a ruling on the club based on the guidance given by the USGA. That is, the official should provide a formal ruling that the club is conforming or non-conforming. If the club most likely conforms, the official should provide a Duration of Competition or Duration of Round Answer that the player may use the club during the competition or round, but that the player must obtain an official conformance determination prior to using the club in subsequent competitions or rounds played under USGA Rules.
            If there is a doubt regarding the conformance of the club and the player's starting time is close, the official should advise the player that he shouldn't carry the club until a determination is made and, should the player choose to carry the club, he is subject to penalty in accordance with Rule 4-1 if the club is ultimately deemed to be non-conforming. Any player who ignores an official's guidance and carries a doubtful club would be subject to penalty in the event of a subsequent non-conforming ruling. This would apply whether the competition was closed or not.
            If the player chooses not to carry the club and it is later confirmed that the club conforms, the official should deliver the club to the player as soon as possible and provide a formal ruling to the player. If it is later determined that the club most likely conforms, the official should deliver the club to the player as soon as possible and provide permission to use the club for the duration of the competition in stroke play (Duration of Competition Answer) or for the duration of the round in match-play (Duration of Round Answer). In either case, the official should not deliver the club to the player during the round if the player started his round with 14 clubs.
          
          
            B. Questions Arising During Stroke Play Competition
          
          
            If the club has already been used, officials should only accept questions between rounds or at the conclusion of play before the competition is closed (but, see Field Procedures, section D below).
            The official should ascertain why the competitor, fellow-competitor or third party is questioning the club.
            If the official is absolutely certain of the correct decision, the competitor should be informed (see Field Procedures, A2).
            If the official is unsure of the ruling, the player should be advised that he will receive either a formal ruling or a Duration of Competition Answer before the close of the competition. The procedure is the same as for a question arising before the competition began (see Field Procedures, A3 - A6).
            If no Duration of Competition Answer is given and it is later confirmed that the club does not conform, then the competitor should be penalized in accordance with Rule 4-1.
          
          
            C. Questions Arising During Match-Play Competition
          
          During a match play event, the above procedure may need to be modified.
          
            If the question arises between rounds, it would be too late for a defeated opponent of the player with a suspect club to make a claim, but a question from him would be grounds for checking the club before the player starts his next round.
            The procedure would be to consult with the player, opponent and/or third-party and obtain appropriate information similar to stroke play. There may be more urgency in this case as it would be desirable to know whether the club is non-conforming before the player starts his next round, which might be the same day.
            If a formal ruling is obtained or a Duration of Round Answer is reached, the player should be told as soon as possible. If the decision is that the club does not conform, the official would warn the player that if he carries the club in the next round, he would be subject to penalty in accordance with Rule 4-1.
            If a player makes a claim during his match that his opponent is carrying a non-conforming club, the official will have to make a ruling under even greater time constraints. Ideally, a ruling should be made before the match is finished. In that event, if there is no clear evidence of non-conformance, the official should almost always err toward ruling the club to conform. However, such a ruling would be considered to be a Duration of Round Answer, and a more formal decision should be made prior to the next round.
            Thereafter, if the opponent wins, the procedure is the same as for a question arising between rounds (see Field Procedures, C1 and C2).
          
          
            D. Questions Arising After Competition Closes
          
          Once a competition has closed, there is plenty of time to contact the USGA to find out whether the club conforms and/or to submit the club. If it turns out that the club is non-conforming, the decision of whether to penalize the player depends on whether he knew the club was non-conforming prior to the close of competition (see Rule 34-1). This is a question of fact, but in determining the facts, the Committee may wish to consider other evidence as well as the player's own statement.
          
            Conclusion
          
          The vast majority of golf clubs conform to the Rules. Therefore, equipment conformance questions are rare. However, questions do arise from time to time, and officials need to know how to deal with them. It is important to remember that it is a player's responsibility to play with conforming clubs. He cannot shift this responsibility to the officials. For their part, officials should respond to such questions calmly and with due consideration to all parties involved. Appropriate consultations should be made (i.e., refer to Rules of Golf, this Guide, contact the USGA, etc.). If it is not possible to give a definitive ruling immediately, a Duration of Competition or Duration of Round Answer should be given.
          In giving Duration of Competition or Duration of Round Answers, officials in doubt should err toward deeming clubs to conform. Penalizing a player for carrying or using a club that later turns out to be conforming is a more serious error than allowing use of a club which later turns out to be non-conforming.
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14608</url>
      <title>Rule 4 - Clubs</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
  
    
      
        
          
            
              Rule 4 - Clubs
            
            Preamble
          
          The preamble to Rule 4 and Appendix II provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  A player in doubt as to the conformity of a club should consult the USGA.
                  A manufacturer should submit to the USGA a sample of a club to be manufactured for a ruling as to whether the club conforms with the Rules. The sample becomes the property of the USGA for reference purposes. If a manufacturer fails to submit a sample or, having submitted a sample, fails to await a ruling before manufacturing and/or marketing the club, the manufacturer assumes the risk of a ruling that the club does not conform with the Rules.
                
              
            
          
          The vast majority of people who play golf assume that when they buy golf clubs, they conform with the Rules. To help prevent non-conforming equipment from appearing in the marketplace, the USGA offers an equipment testing and evaluation service to manufacturers, and encourages manufacturers to submit drawings, descriptions, and/or prototype samples of new product to the USGA as early in the development process as possible, prior to mass production and distribution, in order to avoid potentially costly consequences should the USGA determine that the product does not conform to the Rules of Golf. Additionally, this process helps to protect golfers from unwittingly obtaining non-conforming equipment for use under the Rules of Golf. While this procedure works most of the time, there are occasions when non-conforming equipment is sold in the marketplace. That, combined with the fact that many golfers like to make their own modifications to clubs (see section below on Wear and Alteration), makes the Guide an important tool for all concerned.
          
            Form and Make of Clubs - General (Rule 4-1a)
          
          Rule 4-1a provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  The player's clubs must conform with this Rule and the provisions, specifications and interpretations set forth in Appendix II.
                
              
            
          
          As previously noted, while the USGA's equipment testing and evaluation process works most of the time in preventing non-conforming equipment from entering the marketplace, not all products are submitted to the USGA and some are submitted after they have been mass produced and distributed for sale. Additionally, on very rare occasion, a new or modified Rule can render existing equipment non-conforming.
          As a result, it is the player's responsibility to ensure that his clubs conform to the Rules. The player may consult the USGA, their Rules Committee or the Committee in charge of a competition in which he has entered for assistance in making this assessment.
          
            Wear and Alteration (Rule 4-1b)
          
          Over time, the face and grip of a club, in particular, may become worn through use. For example, a grip may become so worn that it becomes molded for the hands, or the grooves on an iron club may become so worn that they no longer conform to the requirements in Appendix II, 5c.
          Rule 4-1b provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  A club that conforms with the Rules when new is deemed to conform after wear through normal use. Any part of a club that has been purposely altered is regarded as new and must, in its altered stated, conform with the Rules.
                
              
            
          
          This means that a club which conformed when new cannot be rendered non-conforming due to wear through normal use. However, a club which did not conform to the Rules when new cannot be worn into a conforming state. Such a club would always be considered non-conforming. Wear is defined as the erosion of material. Damage, on the other hand, is usually caused by a single occurrence. Generally, material decomposition or deterioration is not considered wear.
          
            Playing Characteristics Changed (Rule 4-2a)
          
          Rule 4-2a provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  During a stipulated round, the playing characteristics of a club must not be purposely changed by adjustment or by any other means.
                
              
            
          
          The purpose of this Rule is to prevent the player from purposely modifying his club during the round, such as modifying a club's lie or loft, adjusting weight or changing the head and/or shaft, regardless of whether the club has been designed to be adjustable.
          
            Foreign Material (Rule 4-2b)
          
          Rule 4-2b provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  Foreign material must not be applied to the club face for the purpose of influencing the movement of the ball.
                
              
            
          
          The Equipment Standards Committee employs this Rule when materials of a temporary nature have been applied to the face - such as saliva, grass juice, chalk, aerosol spray or similar substances. Permanent attachments or coatings such as plasma spray, "balata"-type rubber or even paint are dealt with under the club face Rules in Appendix II (see Section 5).
          The most important question to ask when ruling on a club which has had something temporarily applied to the face by a player is "why has it been put there?" If a material or substance has been applied to the face in order to protect it or to clean it, then it would probably be permitted provided all other Rules are satisfied. However, if the purpose of the application is to influence the movement of the ball or to assist the player in making a stroke, it would be prohibited. Any type of tape or similar material added to the face is not permitted for any purpose.
           
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14609</url>
      <title>Appendix II - Design of Clubs</title>
      <body>
  
  
    
  
  
    Appendix II - Design of Clubs
  
  
    
      
        
           
          
            
              Preamble
            
            
          
          
            As well as advising manufacturers that they should submit clubs to the USGA for a ruling as to their conformity, the preamble to Appendix II also states that:
            
          
          
            
              
                
                  
                    Where a club, or part of a club, is required to meet a specification within the Rules, it must be designed and manufactured with the intention of meeting that specification.
                    
                  
                
              
            
          
          
            This point can be illustrated using Appendix II, 2a, which states, in part, that "The shaft must be straight ..." For the purposes of the Rules, this means that manufacturers are expected to design their shafts with the intention that they will be straight. However, taking into consideration the materials commonly used to make shafts, and the manufacturing techniques involved, it is not always possible for them to be perfectly straight. The preamble to Appendix II requires that the shaft must be designed and manufactured with the intention of being straight (for further example, see Section 2b). As a result, when evaluating shafts for conformance, the USGA may incorporate a reasonable tolerance.
            
          
          
            Appendix II divides the club into five separate categories and describes the specifications that apply to each. The five categories are as follows:
            
          
          1. The Club (in general) 2. The Shaft3. The Grip4. The Clubhead5. The Club Face
          
            The following section will examine the preceding five categories in detail. Each sub-section will begin by stating the relevant rule (shaded in blue) and then explain what is meant by the rule, as well as how to apply it. When the explanations incorporate a specific ‘guideline' which has been adopted by the Equipment Standards Committee, it will be highlighted with blue text.
            
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14617</url>
      <title>Clubs</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
    
      
        
          
            1. Clubs
          
          
          
            a. General
          
          Appendix II, 1a provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  A club is an implement designed to be used for striking the ball and generally comes in three forms: woods, irons and putters distinguished by shape and intended use. A putter is a club with a loft not exceeding ten degrees designed primarily for use on the putting green.
                
              
            
          
          In defining what is meant by the term "club," this Rule makes reference to the three main forms a club traditionally takes, i.e., woods, irons and putters. The terms "wood" and "iron" do not necessarily refer to the material the club is made out of, but rather to the general shape of the clubhead. A "wood" club is one where the head is relatively broad from face to back, and it can be made of materials such as titanium, steel or wood. An "iron" club is one where the head is relatively narrow from face to back, and it is usually made of steel.
          By definition, the loft of a putter must not exceed 10 degrees, and a club with a loft greater than that is normally regarded as an iron club. Putters are permitted to have negative loft. However, a loft of less than -15 degrees would not be considered "traditional and customary in form and make" (See Design of Clubs, Section 1a(i)).
          The Rules and guidelines sometimes distinguish between "wood" and "iron" clubs (see Design of Clubs, Section 5c for an example of where they do). As hybrid, rescue and utility clubs have increased in popularity and design variety, it is sometimes challenging to define whether a particular club should be classified as a wood or an iron. In such cases, the general shape and size of the clubhead should be referenced in order to determine which classification should apply for the purpose of applying the rules. Additionally, there are various instances throughout the Rules where different specifications apply to putters. These differences in the Rules will be highlighted appropriately throughout this Guide.
          As a consequence of these differences, confusion often exists as to which rules apply to "chippers," i.e., iron clubs which are specifically designed to be used just off the putting green with a putting stroke. For clarification on "The Status of a Chipper," see Decision 4-1/3 in "Decisions on the Rules of Golf" and Design of Clubs, Section 1c.
          Appendix II, 1a goes on to state that:
          
            
              
                
                  The club must not be substantially different from the traditionally and customary form and make. The club must be composed of a shaft and a head and it may also have material added to the shaft to enable the player to obtain a firm hold (see 3 below). All parts must be fixed so that the club is one unit, and it must have no external attachments. Exceptions may be made for attachments that do not affect the performance of the club.
                
              
            
          
          In explaining this part of the Rule, it is easier to divide it into the following four sections:
          
            (i) Traditional and Customary Form and Make
          
          The phrase "traditional and customary form and make" does not mean that clubs must look the same as they did 100 years ago. If so, steel shafts and metal woodheads would not conform to the Rules. As noted in the introduction to this Guide, it is not the purpose of the Rules to stifle innovation.
          In practice, the "Traditional and Customary Rule" is rarely used - having been largely superseded by the "Plain in Shape" Rule (see Design of Clubs, Section 4a). However, it is still applied in those cases where the Equipment Standards Committee decides that a particular design deviates from traditional appearance and/or construction standards, but which may not be covered by a more specific provision within the Rules.
          
            (ii) Club Composition
          
          The purpose of this provision is merely to stipulate that multiple shafts and heads are not permitted. It also highlights that it is not necessary for a club to have material added to the shaft for gripping. For further information regarding a club which has no material added to the shaft to form a grip, see Design of Clubs, Section 3.
          
            (iii) All Parts Must Be Fixed
          
          
            This is interpreted to mean that no part of the golf club should be designed to move, nor should it be promoted as doing so. Therefore, if any part of a club were to incorporate moving powder, pellets, liquid, vibrating wires, rollers, tuning forks, or any number of other features which could be considered a "moving part," it would be in breach of this Rule. Additionally, this provision is interpreted to mean that with some exceptions, when assembled, all parts are bonded such that they require heating to loosen. Of course, this does not apply to clubs with permitted adjustable features.
          
            (iv) External Attachments
          
          In 2008, the USGA amended the wording of the provision relating to external attachments in order to accommodate a change in interpretation, which previously prohibited any "external attachments" to the club (with certain specific exceptions). While the Rule continues to prohibit the attachment of anything to the club which could potentially have an effect on its performance (e.g., aiming bars or weights), other items may now be permitted to be attached to certain parts of the club provided (a) no performance benefit can be derived, and (b) no other Rules are breached, including Rule 14-3 (Artificial Devices, Unusual Equipment and Unusual Use of Equipment).
          Prior to 2008, two notable exceptions to this Rule included the permission to apply lead tape to the shaft or clubhead for weighting (see also Design of Clubs, Section 1b and Decision 4-1/4 in "Decisions on the Rules of Golf") and the use of a suction cup at the end of the shaft of a putter to assist with retrieving the ball from the hole. Even though these exceptions may be considered counter to the provisions in this guideline, use of these items will continue to be permitted on traditional grounds.
          The change in wording reflects a broadening of the types of items which may be attached to an existing club, provided the items meet the given criteria:
          
            Temporary, non-permanent attachments to the shaft, such as decals for identification or tape to protect the shaft (also permitted prior to 2008). Such attachments, for identification only, may also be permitted on the clubhead, other than the face. However, such attachments must not serve any other purpose, such as for alignment. In the case of driving clubs, such attachments must not be applied in a manner that would cause any confusion with the correct identification of a driving club on the List of Conforming Driver Heads. In other words, any such attachments must be subtle, plain in appearance and discreetly positioned.
            Temporary, non-permanent attachments to the shaft, such as clip-on devices, provided such items do not excessively protrude from the shaft, their cross-section conforms to the shape of the shaft, and are sufficiently fixed. Other clip-on devices that do not conform to the shape of the shaft, such as a club prop for use in wet weather, may be attached to the shaft provided such devices are removed prior to making a stroke.
            Temporary, non-permanent attachments to the butt end of the grip, such as tee pegs, ball markers or ball retrieval devices: provided such items do not cause the grip to be considered molded for the hands or create a bulge or waist in the grip; andthe outer diameter of such an item is less than or equal to the outer diameter of the butt end of the grip and the item does not extend beyond the butt end of the grip by more than 2 inches (50.8 mm).other temporary, non-permanent attachments to any part of the grip, other than the butt end, provided such items are removed prior to making a stroke. However, tape or gauze applied to the full length of the grip is permitted, provided the grip conforms in its modified state.
            Other material added to the shaft, such as for alignment purposes, provided the material is considered semi-permanent. "Semi-permanent" is interpreted to mean durable and not easily removable. Additionally, it must not be re-usable and/or must be essentially destroyed upon removal. However, such application must not breach Rule 14-3.
            Attachments to the clubhead (other than the face), such as protective coverings, decorative items or alignment aids, provided the item is semi-permanent. However, such items must not excessively protrude from the clubhead and must conform to the shape of the clubhead. Additionally, for driving clubs, such attachments must not serve to cause any confusion with the correct identification of a driving club on the List of Conforming Driver Heads. Permanent additions to a clubhead are considered a part of the head and, therefore, the head, in its modified state, would have to conform to the Rules of Golf, particularly the requirements of Rule 4a, Appendix II (i.e., ‘plain in shape' and dimensions).
          
          
          
            b. Adjustability
          
          Appendix II, 1b provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  All clubs may incorporate features for weight adjustment. Other forms of adjustability may also be permitted upon evaluation by the USGA. The following requirements apply to all permissible methods of adjustment:
                  (i) the adjustment cannot be readily made;
                  (ii) all adjustable parts are firmly fixed and there is no reasonable likelihood of them working loose during a round; and
                  (iii) all configurations of adjustment conform with the Rules.
                  During a stipulated round, the playing characteristics of a club must not be purposely changed by adjustment or by any other means (see Rule 4-2a).
                
              
            
          
          
            (i) General
          
          In order to preserve the integrity of Rule 4-2 (Playing Characteristics Changed), this Rule clearly states that it must not be too easy for a player to make adjustments during the course of a stipulated round. This is interpreted to mean that adjustments must require the use of a special tool, such as an Allen key, a Phillips screwdriver or a custom-made tool or device. It must not be possible to make the adjustment just by using the fingers, or some other object which would normally be kept in a golfer's pocket, such as a coin or a pitch-mark repair tool.
          The above restrictions have been included in the Rules in order to encourage the player to make all of the necessary adjustments to his clubs before starting his round, and to protect him from either unwittingly or purposely making adjustments during a round.
          
            (ii) Adjustability for Weight
          
          All clubs may be designed to be adjustable for weight, provided the adjustment mechanism conforms to the conditions described previously and in Appendix II, 1b of the Rules. An example of what would and would not be permitted is illustrated below.
          
            
          
          As noted in Design of Clubs, Section 1a, with respect to adjustments for weight, the only exception to the conditions described in (i) above is the addition or removal of lead tape. This is a practice which pre-dates the introduction of the adjustability rules and is permitted on "traditional" grounds. The addition or removal of lead tape during a round is not permitted (see Rule 4-2a and Decision 4-2/0.5 in "Decisions on the Rules of Golf").
          
            (iii) Other Kinds of Adjustability
          
          In 2008, the USGA relaxed the Rules regarding adjustability to allow all clubs, including woods and irons, to be designed to be adjustable in ways other than for weight. However, such adjustment features are subject to evaluation by the USGA, and manufacturers are encouraged to submit all adjustable design innovations to the USGA in the early stages of development.
          Examples of other forms of adjustability include a putter designed to be adjustable for lie and/or length. Additionally, while some head/shaft assembly systems have been evaluated by the USGA and found to conform to the Rules of Golf, not all systems are considered conforming. Please consult the USGA to determine which systems conform to the Rules. Again, all permissible methods of adjustment must require the use of a special tool, not just the fingers or a coin, etc. If, as is often the case, a screw is used to fix the adjustable mechanism, the club must, for all practicable purposes, be unusable without the screw being in place and tightly fixed. As an exception to this unusable requirement, the USGA has permitted the long putter which can be dismantled into two shorter lengths for travel purposes. A screw-together ("pool-cue") joint is permitted with an Allen screw, or something similar, that penetrates the threaded section of the joint by at least halfway.
          When assessing the conformity of an adjustable club, it is important to remember the third condition listed in Appendix II, 1b, and to ensure that the club cannot be adjusted into a position which does not conform to the Rules. For example, a putter which is adjustable for lie must not be capable of being adjusted into a position where the shaft diverges from the vertical by less than ten degrees (see Appendix II, 1d and Design of Clubs, Section 1d), or any other position which would render the club non-conforming.
          
            
          
          
          
            c. Length
          
          Appendix II, 1c provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  The overall length of the club must be at least 18 inches (0.457 m) and, except for putters, must not exceed 48 inches (1.219 m).
                
              
            
          
          This Rule is straightforward, and the measurement of woods and irons is well described and illustrated in both the Rules and the of Golf." The measurement of length for putters can be illustrated as follows:
          
            
          
          
            Please note that the Equipment Standards Committee has adopted a position that clubs designed for chipping, including modified wedges, that are longer than standard-length clubs of similar loft are not traditional and customary in form and make (see Appendix II, 1a).  The following table is used for the purpose of determining the maximum allowable length of a chipping club.
           
          
            
              
                Loft Range/Length
                 
              
              
                Minimum Loft (°)
                16
                20
                23
                26
                29
                33
                37
                41
                45
              
              
                Maximum Loft (°)
                19
                22
                25
                28
                32
                36
                40
                44
                48
              
              
                Maximum Allowable Length (in)
                41.5
                41
                40.5
                40
                39.5
                39
                38.5
                38
                37.5
              
              
                Maximum Allowable Length (m)
                1.054
                1.041
                1.029
                1.016
                1.003
                0.991
                0.978
                0.965
                0.953
              
            
          
           
          
          
            d. Alignment
          
          Appendix II, 1d provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  When the club is in its normal address position the shaft must be so aligned that:
                  (i) the projection of the straight part of the shaft on to the vertical plane through the toe and heel must diverge from the vertical by at least 10 degrees. If the overall design of the club is such that the player can effectively use the club in a vertical or close-to-vertical position, the shaft may be required to diverge from the vertical in this plane by as much as 25 degrees;
                  (ii) the projection of the straight part of the shaft on to the vertical plane along the intended line of play must not diverge from the vertical by more than 20 degrees forward or 10 degrees backward.
                
              
            
          
          This Rule is particularly relevant to putters, and it exists mainly as a means for disallowing croquet or vertical-pendulum style putters (with vertical shafts) and shuffle-board style strokes, as well as designs which facilitate such strokes (see Figure 4).
          
            
          
          For most putters, the "normal address position" is determined by the geometry of the head. The head would be placed on a horizontal flat surface, with the sole touching that surface at a point directly below the center of the face. The shaft angle is measured with the head in this position (see Figure 5).
          
            
          
          
            If the putter head shape or weight distribution is very asymmetric, it may be necessary to make a subjective judgment as to where the effective center of the face is, and then to sole the club directly below that point. The position of the head in this instance may not always be the position that was intended by design. Nonetheless, in some cases, a judgment must be made based on how the club could feasibly and effectively be used (see Figure 6).
          
          
            
          
          The same subjectivity may also be needed when confronted with a putter which has a very curved sole (see Figure 7). As before, the Equipment Standards Committee takes into account not only the manner in which the putter is designed to be used, but also the way it could feasibly and effectively be used, given the geometry of the head as well as other unique characteristics of the overall design. This interpretation is particularly relevant to long-shafted putters with very curved or multi-planed soles - however, standard-length putters of approximately 34 to 38 inches may also be subjected to this assessment.
          
            
          
          It should be noted that all putters can usually be positioned in such a way that the shaft diverges from the vertical by less than 10 degrees or even to a position where the shaft itself is vertical. Also, it is unusual for the sole of a putter to be completely flat all the way from heel to toe. When faced with a ruling of this kind, the decision should not be based on whether a player uses the putter with the shaft in a position of less than 10 degrees - but whether the putter design facilitates a player placing the shaft in a position of less than 10 degrees (see Figure 8).
          
            
          
          
            If the overall design of a putter is such that the player can achieve a "vertical-pendulum" style stroke (i.e., putt effectively with the shaft in a vertical or near-vertical position), it would be ruled contrary to Appendix II, 1d, even if the shaft angle does satisfy the 10-degree Rule when the putter is in its "normal address position." The shaft angle on such a putter could be required to be increased to as much as 25 degrees. In assessing whether a putter can be used effectively in a "vertical-pendulum" style manner, the combination of the following features should be considered:
          
            length of shaft
            position of shaft attachment to head
            angle of shaft in toe-to-heel plane and front-to-back plane
            shape and weight distribution of head
            curvature and shape of sole
            intent of the design
          
          Even though each of these putter features, when considered separately, could conform to the Rules, the combination of the features might lead to a decision that the putter does not conform.
          This is an extremely good example of an area where rules officials should take care not to make a decision unless they are 100% certain they are correct. If, after examining the club and carrying out all of the appropriate consultations, it is still not possible to give a definitive ruling, a Duration of Competition or Duration of Round Answer should be given (see Field Procedures - Guidance to Rules Officials Concerning Questions on the Conformity of Clubs at Competitions).
          The determination of a feasible "normal address position" or whether a putter can be used with the shaft in a vertical or close-to-vertical position can be highly subjective and, in terms of those putters actually submitted to the USGA, the job of making rulings is easier because it is possible to compare them with previous submissions and decisions.
          Appendix II, 1d goes on to state that:
          
            
              
                
                  Except for putters, all of the heel portion of the club must lie within 0.625 inches (15.58 mm) of the plane containing the axis of the straight part of the shaft and the intended (horizontal) line of play.
                
              
            
          
          The intent of this rule is to prevent center shafted clubs (see Design of Clubs, Section 2c - Attachment to the Clubhead). The measurement is illustrated in Figure 9. For unusually shaped heads (e.g., square driver heads), the outermost point on the heel may be located at a point significantly back from the face. As such, the measurement would be completed at that point.
          
            
          
          As provided in the Rule, in most cases, the shaft of a putter may be attached at any point on the clubhead (see Section 2c).
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14618</url>
      <title>Shafts</title>
      <body>
  
  
    
      
        
          
            2. Shafts 
          
          
            a. Straightness 
          Appendix II, 2a provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  The shaft must be straight from the top of the grip to a point not more than 5 inches (127 mm) above the sole, measured from the point where the shaft ceases to be straight along the axis of the bent part of the shaft and/or socket.
                
              
            
          
          This Rule implies that the shaft must extend to the end of the grip, or at least that the grip should not extend beyond the top end of the shaft more than is necessary to accommodate the butt cap (see Figure 10).
          
             
          The "5-inch" measurement should be made using a pair of calipers, to measure the depth of the head at the point where the shaft is attached, and a flexible measuring tape, or a piece of string, to measure along the axis of the shaft (see Figure 11).It is not possible to measure a bend in a shaft accurately using a normal, stiff ruler. The point where the shaft ceases to be straight can be determined by placing a rigid steel ruler along the straight part of the shaft and identifying the point where the shaft and the ruler are no longer in contact. This rule is particularly relevant for putters where the shaft is inserted directly into the head. (For putter heads with "necks," see Design of Clubs, Section 2c.)
          
             
          
          
            b. Bending and Twisting Properties 
          Appendix II, 2b requires that:
          
            
              
                
                  At any point along its length, the shaft must:
                  (i) bend in such a way that the deflection is the same regardless of how the shaft is rotated about its longitudinal axis; and
                  (ii) twist the same amount in both directions.
                
              
            
          
          This Rule effectively restricts shafts from being designed to have asymmetric properties, so that however the club is assembled, or whichever way the shaft is oriented, it will make no difference to the performance of the club.
          However, many graphite shafts have a small "spine" running along the length of the shaft which may make them bend differently depending on how they are fitted to the head. As previously noted, the USGA recognizes that it is difficult for manufacturers to consistently produce a perfectly symmetrical shaft and, provided that the shaft is manufactured with the intention of meeting the above requirements, the USGA may incorporate a reasonable tolerance when evaluating shafts for conformance. Additionally, manufacturers of clubs may orient or align shafts which have spines for uniformity in assembling sets, or in an effort to make the shafts perform as if they were perfectly symmetrical. However, a shaft which has been oriented for the purpose of influencing the performance of a club, e.g., to correct wayward shots, would be contrary to the intent of this Rule.
          It's difficult to assess the conformance of a shaft in the field. A standard shaft with a circular cross-section would most likely conform to the Rules unless there is evidence to the contrary (e.g., claims by the manufacturer which would indicate non-conformance, including advertising claims). However, a shaft which is not symmetrical in cross-section, such as an oval or rectangular shaft, would not normally be expected to conform to the Rules. Manufacturers of shafts with unique cross-sections should submit them to the USGA early in the development process, prior to production and marketing.
          
          
            c. Attachment to Clubhead 
          Appendix II, 2c requires that:
          
            
              
                
                  The shaft must be attached to the clubhead at the heel either directly or through a single plain neck and/or socket. The length from the top of the neck and/or socket to the sole of the club must not exceed 5 inches (127 mm), measured along the axis of, and following any bend in, the neck and/or socket.
                  
                    Exception for Putters: The shaft or neck or socket of a putter may be fixed at any point in the head.
                
              
            
          
          The most important points to remember here are that a club must only have one neck, that it must be "plain", and, in order to restrict elaborate shapes and curves, the length of the neck is limited to 5 inches (127 mm). This measurement should be made in the same way as a bend in the bottom of a shaft (see Design of Clubs, Section 2a).
          The majority of necks are designed to have the shaft inserted into them, and this normally avoids any confusion as to where the neck begins. However, if the neck is inserted into the shaft, the measurement should be taken from the end of the shaft.
          The interpretation of a "plain" neck has recently been clarified as follows:
          
            All Clubs 
          The neck must not be shaped for any purpose, other than connecting the shaft to the head in a traditional manner. While a neck may contain features such as an adjustability mechanism, a method for damping vibration or an alignment line, it must not be unusually shaped in order to house or accomodate such a feature. For example, in most cases, lines which have been painted or lightly engraved onto an otherwise plain neck are permitted. However, a neck designed specifically to accomodate such lines or marks would be considered non-conforming. Small scale features, on an otherwise plain neck, which are purely for decorative purposes, and could not effectively perform, or be used for, another purpose, may also be permitted.
          
            Woods 
          The above requirements also apply to woods. However, there is some accomodation for the transition area between the head of a wood and its neck. This transistion area must fit within a cylinder of a diameter and height of 1 inch (25.4 mm) measured from the base of the transition and parallel to the axis of the shaft. Any transition which satisfies this restriction should be permitted provided it does not contain any other non-plain feature (for example, holes or alignment bars).
          NOTE: Some exceptions may be made for clubheads made of wood. Ferrules shaped to circumvent this interpretation are not permitted.
          Figure 12 contains diagrams of various neck features which would not be considered "plain," such as a putter which has multiple necks and a putter with a neck which is too long.
          
             
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14619</url>
      <title>The Grip</title>
      <body>
  
     
  
    
      
        
          
            
              
                
                  3. The Grip 
                
                
                  a. Definition 
                Appendix II, 3 begins by stating that:
                
                  
                    
                      
                        The grip consists of material added to the shaft to enable the player to obtain a firm hold. The grip must be fixed to the shaft, must be straight and plain in form, must extend to the end of the shaft and must not be molded for any part of the hands. If no material is added, that portion of the shaft designed to be held by the player must be considered the grip.
                      
                    
                  
                
                The grip is principally for the purpose of assisting the player in obtaining a firm hold - so that the club does not slip or twist out of the player's hand. However, the installation of a grip is optional.
                
                  When no material is added to the part of the shaft designed to be held by the player, the Rules relating to the grip take precedence over the Rules relating to the shaft. Therefore, the dimensions and cross-section of that area of the shaft may change and equal bending in any direction would not be required (see Design of Clubs, Section 2b).
                
                  In order to accommodate both hands, the grip must be at least seven inches (177.8 mm) in length. This also applies to clubs which have been designed to be used one-handed. For putters with two grips, see The Grip, Section 3c.
                Due to the nature of grips and the Rules regulating them, it is sometimes very difficult to make a ruling without examining and comparing examples of other grips which are known to either conform or not conform. However, this is not something which would normally be possible in the field. It may help to remember that the overall consideration is that a grip "must not be molded for any part of the hands." If a certain feature on the grip enables the player to place his hands in exactly the same position every time, solely by feel and without actually looking at the grip, then it must be determined whether that feature renders the grip "molded for the hands." An extreme example of a grip which would be ruled "molded for the hands" is the type of "training grip" often used to help beginners. However, a grip which has subtle changes in surface texture would usually be considered conforming. Likewise, printed markings which assist with the correct placement of the hands visually would normally be considered conforming. Most of the details contained in Design of Clubs, Sections 3b and 3c serve to clarify and expand on this basic principle.
                
                
                  b. Cross-section 
                Appendix II, 3(i) through (iv) provide more specific parameters for the grip and states that:
                
                  
                    
                      
                        (i) For clubs other than putters the grip must be circular in cross-section, except that a continuous, straight, slightly raised rib may be incorporated along the full length of the grip, and a slightly indented spiral is permitted on a wrapped grip or replica of one.
                        (ii) A putter grip may have a non-circular cross-section, provided the cross-section has no concavity, is symmetrical and remains generally similar throughout the length of the grip.
                        (iii) The grip may be tapered but must not have any bulge or waist. Its cross-sectional dimensions measured in any direction must not exceed 1.75 inches (44.45 mm).
                        (iv) For clubs other than putters the axis of the grip must coincide with the axis of the shaft.
                      
                    
                  
                
                
                  (i) Circular Cross-Section Requirement (Woods and Irons) 
                Grips on woods and iron clubs are allowed to deviate from circular by having a slightly raised rib running along the full length of the grip (often called a "reminder rib").
                
                  "Slightly raised" is interpreted to mean that the maximum and minimum diameters of the cross-section at any point must not differ by more than 0.040 inches (1.016 mm). Additionally, the dimension of the rib width, from edge to edge, should not exceed 50% of the grip's internal diameter. While the first measurement can be taken using a pair of calipers, due to the nature of gripping materials, caution should be taken in making decisions in the field.
                
                  In the case of a standard length grip (approximately 10 inches (254 mm) in length), the "full length of the grip" is interpreted to mean that the rib must extend to within 3 inches (76.2 mm) of the tip. This is generally regarded as enough to cover the span of the player's hands on the grip (see Figure 13). 
                
                  Simulated leather wrapped grips molded out of a rubber-like material with an indented spiral surface pattern or other similar indentations are permitted, as long as the fingers cannot comfortably fit in between the spirals or indentations. Also, features such as lines, dots, or other patterned indentations, which are too small to fit even the smallest of fingers, would not of themselves cause a grip to be in breach of the Rules. Such features would not normally render a grip non-circular in cross-section (for irons and woods) or not generally similar throughout the length of the grip (putters). 
                
                   
                
                  (ii) Putter Grips 
                As clearly stated in the Rule, a putter grip may have a non circular cross-section, provided that, among other things, the cross-section remains generally similar throughout the length of the grip.
                
                  In order to accommodate the popular (and somewhat traditional) "pistol-type" putter grips, the phrase "generally similar" is interpreted to mean: (i) that the butt (top) end of the grip should not involve a sharp change in slope or dramatic flare on the underside (see Figures 14(a) and (b)); (ii) that the flat front must extend to within 1 inch (25.4 mm) of the top and bottom ends (see Figures 14(b) and (c)); and (iii) if the axis of the grip and the shaft do not coincide, the grip must be at least 10 inches (254 mm) in length. 
                
                   
                As with circular grips, features such as lines, dots, or other patterned indentations, which are too small to fit even the smallest of fingers, would not of themselves render a putter grip not generally similar throughout the length of the grip or molded for the hands.
                
                  (iii) Cross-Sectional Dimension 
                This clause is self-explanatory and illustrated in the Rules of Golf. If needed, manufacturers should contact the USGA for further guidance.
                
                  (iv) Grip Axis 
                This clause merely reinforces that the grip on a wood or iron club must be circular. It also requires that the axis of the grip and shaft must coincide. In other words, a grip made for a wood or iron club must not be manufactured such that, when installed, it is not centered on the shaft.
                
                
                  c. Two Grips 
                Appendix II, 3(v) provides that:
                
                  
                    
                      
                        A putter may have two grips provided that each is circular in cross-section, the axis of each coincides with the axis of the shaft, and they are separated by at least 1.5 inches (38.1 mm).
                      
                    
                  
                
                If a putter were allowed to have two non-circular grips, it would be possible to mount the grips such that their cross-section would not be "generally similar" throughout the entire length (see Design of Clubs, Section 3b). For this reason, putters which have two grips must have two circular grips and this is interpreted strictly to mean that the grips must not incorporate a reminder rib.
                Where a putter has two grips, these grips are only considered "separate" if the gap between them is at least 1.5 inches (38.1 mm) in length. If such a gap does not exist, the total length from the bottom of the lower "grip" to the top of the upper one is considered "one grip." Therefore, in both of the instances mentioned above, it is unlikely that the grip would conform if two conventional grips were used. Either the exposed piece of shaft between the two "grips" would constitute a waist, or the fact that two grips met in the middle would cause a bulge. The second example may be overcome if the lower grip was a continuation of the top grip, that is, a continuation of the same taper (see Figure 15).
                
                  If a putter does have two grips, the upper grip must be at least 5 inches (127 mm) in length. If the grip does not satisfy this requirement, it would be considered to be ‘molded for the hands'. 
                Note that it is not permissible for wood or iron clubs, including chippers, to have more than one grip.
                
                   
              
            
           
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14621</url>
      <title>Club Head</title>
      <body>
  
    4. Clubhead 
  
     
  
    
      
        
          
          
            a. Plain in Shape 
          The "plain in shape" requirement in Appendix II, 4a originates from the "traditional and customary" requirement in Appendix II, 1a. It is generally a descriptive rule, although in reality, it is challenging to define exactly what a golf club can or should look like. The following section assists in explaining what is and what is not permitted, but it should be noted that this is not an all-inclusive list. Even if a clubhead satisfies all of the points outlined below, there may still be features or characteristics which render it not generally plain in shape. An overall assessment of the appearance of the head should always be made. 
          The general provision of Rule 4a, Appendix II provides that:
          
            
              
                
                  The clubhead must be generally plain in shape. All parts must be rigid, structural in nature and functional. The clubhead or its parts must not be designed to resemble any other object.
                
              
            
          
          This provision basically means that the design of the clubhead must be free from gimmicks (though putters are viewed more liberally than woods and irons), must have the general appearance of a clubhead, must not have the appearance of another object, or incorporate certain features which are designed to resemble another object (see Figure 16). All parts of the head must be rigid throughout their length, including permanent, permissible appendages. As a general guideline, "rigid" means that it must not be possible to bend or flex any part of the clubhead by hand (see Figure 17). 
          
             
          
             
          Rule 4a, Appendix II acknowledges that defining whether a clubhead is "plain in shape" is not easy. However, the USGA modified the wording in 2008 to help better define what is intended by this Rule. The Rule now reflects the more liberalized application for putters, which has evolved over the years and provides more detail regarding what is and is not permitted for iron heads and woodheads.
          Rule 4a, Appendix II goes on to state that:
          
            
              
                
                  It is not practicable to define plain in shape precisely and comprehensively. However, features which are deemed to be in breach of this requirement and are therefore not permitted include, but are not limited to:
                  
                    (i) All Clubs 
                  
                    holes through the face;
                    holes through the head (some exceptions may be made for putters and cavity back irons);
                    facsimiles of golf balls or actual golf balls incorporated into the head;
                    features that are for the purpose of meeting dimensional specifications;
                    features that extend into or ahead of the face;
                    features that extend significantly above the top line of the head;
                    furrows in or runners on the head that extend into the face (some exceptions may be made for putters); and
                    optical or electronic devices.
                  
 
              
            
          
          
            Holes Through the Face 
          Holes through the face are not permitted for any club (see Figure 18).
          
             
          
             
          
            Holes Through the Head 
          
            Holes through the head are not permitted for woodheads (see Figure 19).
            Holes through the head are not permitted for iron heads. However, features within the cavity back of an iron head that form a hole or holes may be permitted (e.g., support bars), provided that the feature is contained within the outline of the main body of the head and the hole or holes cannot be viewed from above (see Figure 20).
            
               
            This provision is interpreted very liberally for putters, and holes through the head for any purpose (excluding the face), including aiming, sighting or alignment are permitted, excluding the face (see Figure 21 for examples of permissible holes through the head of a putter).
          
          
             
          
            Facsimiles of Golf Balls 
          This provision is fairly straightforward. Generally, features that are spherical or semi-spherical in nature, whether or not they contain dimples, may be considered to be facsimiles (see Figure 22 for examples of conforming and non-conforming designs). However, other features may be considered facsimiles and are evaluated on a case-by-case basis.
          
             
          
            Features for the Purpose of Meeting Dimensional Specifications 
          Appendix II, 4b requires that, for all clubs, the distance from the heel to the toe of the clubhead must be greater than the distance from the front to the back (see Design of Clubs, Sections 4b(i), (ii) and (iii)). Clubs which incorporate features that are designed to or have the effect of circumventing this requirement are not permitted (see Figure 23).
          
             
          
            Features That Extend Into or Ahead of the Face 
          
            Permitted features in or on the main body of the head must not extend into the face of an iron or wood club, including any alignment features on the crown (see Figure 24). Traditionally, engraved or inscribed alignment lines are generally permitted on iron clubs.
            
               
            Certain features are permitted to extend into the face of a putter, including alignment features and concavities (or furrows) on the crown. However, such features must not have a depth or height greater than 0.25 inches (6.35 mm) when measured in relation to the top line of the face.
            Features of any nature that extend ahead of the face are not permitted on any club (see Figure 25).
          
          
             
          
            Features That Extend Significantly Above the Top Line of the Head 
          
            For putters, alignment or other features must not extend above the top line of the face by more than 0.25 inches (6.35 mm), (see Figure 26).
            
               
            For woods and irons, features which otherwise meet the requirements for "plain in shape" must not extend above the top line of the head by more than 0.1 inches (2.54 mm).
            Permanent or semi-permanent lines or other markings which have been painted, inscribed or otherwise incorporated (see Design of Clubs, Section 1a) for alignment purposes are permitted.
          
          
            Furrows or Runners 
          
            Furrows or runners which extend into the face of a wood or iron club from any part of the head are not permitted (see Figure 27).
            
               
            While this provision is strictly applied to furrows or runners which may appear on the sole of a putter, exceptions may be made for other parts of the putter head (see Figure 28).
          
          
             
          Furrows and/or runners are deemed to extend into the face if the edge of the face has any concavity (point of inflection or turning point). This can be determined by placing a straight edge along the edge of the face. If a runner has been chamfered back, away from the face, by at least 45 degrees, the runner would not be considered to extend into the face (see Figure 29). 
          
             
          
            Optical and Electronic Devices 
          Clubheads that incorporate - for example, prisms, mirrors, reflective materials, light beams, metronomes or mechanical devices such as spirit levels, or other similar devices - are not permitted (see Figures 30 and 31).
          
             
          Electronic devices in or on the club shaft or grip, which have the sole purpose of identifying the club, may be permitted. The identification information is restricted to: 
          
            (a) the club's owner, such as address and phone number;
            (b) inventory tracking information;
            (c) detection of the club's use during the round.
          
          Any such device must meet all other Rules and associated guidelines and must not vibrate or emit light or sound. If the device is capable of any function other than identification, the golf club will be considered not traditional and customary in form and make (see Section 1a(i) and, therefore, non-conforming.
          NOTE: Any system used in conjunction with a club incorporating such a device must comply with the Local Rule Permitting the Use of Distance Measuring Devices (see Note to Rule 14-3 of the Rules of Golf and Appendix I, Part B Section 9) and the USGA-R&amp;amp;A Joint Statement on Electronic Devices.
          Rule 4a, Appendix II states additional specifications for woods and irons:
          
            
              
                
                  
                    (ii) Woods and Irons 
                  
                    all features listed in (i) above;
                    cavities in the outline of the heel and/or the toe of the head that can be viewed from above;
                    severe or multiple cavities in the outline of the back of the head that can be viewed from above;
                    transparent material added to the head with the intention of rendering conforming a feature that is not otherwise permitted; and
                    features that extend beyond the outline of the head when viewed from above.
                  
 
              
            
          
          
            Cavities in the Outline of the Heel and/or Toe 
          This provision applies to cavities in the outline of the heel and/or toe when "viewed from above." When making this assessment, viewed from above is interpreted to mean the range from directly above the head to the normal address position for that club. This restriction does not apply to horizontal cavities around the skirt of the head, which might be visible from above (e.g., horizontal slots or indentations such as the speed slot (see Figures 32a and b)).
          
            Severe or Multiple Cavities in the Outline of the Back of the Head 
          A severe cavity is one in which the entrance of the cavity is narrower than its width at any other point. Multiple cavities are not permitted (see Figures 32c and d). Cavities in the crown of the head are permitted, even if they are primarily designed for sighting, aiming or head alignment, or to accommodate markings for such aids (see Figure 32e). However, cavities in the crown of a driver head are filled for the purposes of evaluating the head's volume (see Design of Clubs, Section 4b(i)).
          
             
          
            Transparent Material 
          
            Clubheads made entirely of transparent material are permitted.
            Transparent material that is added to an otherwise non-plain head does not render the head "plain in shape." For example, a woodhead with a vertical hole from the top surface through to the sole would be ruled non-conforming (see Design of Clubs, Section 4a(i)). Filling this hole with a transparent material (e.g., perspex or glass), would not alter this ruling.
          
          
            Features Extending Beyond the Outline of the Head 
          Any fin, knob, plate or other appendage which protrudes beyond the outline of the head is not permitted for any purpose.
          Note: While this provision is not applied to putters, the USGA has determined that unusual features which protrude beyond the outline of the heel and/or toe of the putter head are usually considered not generally plain in shape or not traditional. However, as previously noted in other parts of this section, other permanent appendages to the putter head are permitted, provided that:
          
            the feature is rigid throughout its length (i.e., cannot be bent or flexed by hand);
            the feature does not extend forward of the face; and,
            the feature does not extend above the top line of the face by more than 0.25 inches (6.35 mm).
          
          
          
            b. Dimensions, Volume and Moment of Inertia 
          Appendix II, 4b is divided into three categories - woods, irons and putters. The volume and moment of inertia limits apply only to woodheads.
          
            
              
                
                  
                    (i) Woods 
                  When the club is in a 60 degree lie angle, the dimensions of the clubhead must be such that:
                  
                    the distance from the heel to the toe of the clubhead is greater than the distance from the face to the back;
                    the distance from the heel to the toe of the clubhead is not greater than 5 inches (127 mm); and
                    the distance from the sole to the crown of the clubhead, including any permitted features, is not greater than 2.8 inches (71.12 mm).
                  
 
              
            
          
          Please refer to "The Rules of Golf" for a description and illustrations of where these measurements should be made. When performing such measurements in the field, the best method is to use a pair of calipers. For the heel to toe measurement, a rigid, straight edge can be held upright against the extremity of the toe end.
          
            Volume Limit: 
          
            
              
                
                  The volume of the clubhead must not exceed 460 cubic centimeters (28.06 cubic inches), plus a tolerance of 10 cubic centimeters (0.61 cubic inches).
                
              
            
          
          This Rule was introduced in 2004 due to the trend of increasing driver head sizes. The Equipment Standards Committee determined that woodheads larger than those already permitted were not traditional and customary. Many woodheads in the marketplace incorporate markings on the sole or other part of the head to indicate approximate volume. However, there is a fairly simple method of measuring clubhead volume, which is based on the displacement of water. By submerging a clubhead in a large measuring container, partially filled with water, the amount that the water rises indicates the head's volume.
          A more accurate method, but not that much more complicated, is the use of a similar container of water placed on a digital weighing scale. With either method, the head is submerged to a point just above the crown (i.e., the hosel is not included).
          Archimedes' Principle states that the buoyant force on a submerged object is equal to the weight of the fluid that is displaced by the object - and since water has a specific gravity of 1.0, this means that 1 cubic centimeter of water has a mass of 1 gram. Therefore, the container of water should be placed on the scale and the weight should be set to zero. When the head is submerged in the water, the weight displayed on the scale (in grams) is equivalent to the volume of the head (in cubic centimeters).
          
             
          In situations where a club is marked with a "cc" value which is in excess of the Rule (i.e., above 460 cubic centimeters), the Committee's policy is to rule that the club is non-conforming - regardless of the actual volume measurement. This is to avoid confusion in the marketplace.
          Prior to measuring the volume of a clubhead, the head should be inspected for cavities. All cavities on the crown should be filled with waterproof clay or other similar material using a straight-line method which connects the edges of the cavity. The straight-line method does not follow the taper or curvature of the surface of the head, rather the cavity is filled so that it becomes a flat surface which adjoins the outer edges.
          Only significant cavities in the sole will be filled. We define significant as any cavity or series of cavities which have a collective volume of greater than 15cc. 
          
            Moment of Inertia (MOI) Limit: 
          
            
              
                
                  When the club is in a 60 degree lie angle, the moment of inertia component around the vertical axis through the clubhead's center of gravity must not exceed 5900 g cm2 (32.359 oz in2), plus a test tolerance of 100 g cm2 (0.547 oz in2).
                
              
            
          
          The MOI of a driver head is a measurement of its resistance to twisting and, therefore, it is one indication of the ‘forgiveness' of a clubhead.
          The measurement of MOI is one of only a few limits within the Rules which cannot be easily performed in the field. This is because the MOI measurement requires specialized equipment and the head must be removed from the shaft. However, drivers with higher MOI measurements are generally represented by models manufactured in recent years and, as a result, have been routinely submitted to the USGA or R&amp;amp;A due to the publication of the List of Conforming Driver Heads.
          The MOI of a driver head is directly related to the head's weight, as well as to the distribution of the head's weight. As a result, a driver head which is designed to be adjustable for weight must conform to the Rules in all available configurations (see Design of Clubs, Section 1b). Additionally, a player who adds additional weight to the driver head, such as with the addition of lead tape, must be certain that the driver head still conforms to the Rules (see Rule 4-1b). To assist golfers with this determination, the Committee will notify a manufacturer that has submitted a driver head having an MOI which is close to the limit, to advise its customers that the addition of any weights to that particular head, including lead tape, other than the weights supplied by the manufacturer for that particular head, is not permitted as it would likely render the club non-conforming.
          
            
              
                
                  
                    (ii) Irons 
                  When the clubhead is in its normal position, the dimensions of the head must be such that the distance from the heel to the toe is greater than the distance from the face to the back.
                
              
            
          
          In practice, due to the shape and size of iron heads, this Rule is rarely violated. It is retained, in part, to help maintain the traditional shape by which irons are recognized. However, it appears that hybrid irons are becoming more common and, as a result, this Rule may have even greater utility in the future.
          
            
              
                
                  
                    (iii) Putters 
                  When the clubhead is in its normal address position, the dimensions of the head must be such that:
                  
                    the distance from the heel to the toe is greater than the distance from the face to the back;
                    the distance from the heel to the toe of the head is less than or equal to 7 inches (177.8 mm);
                    the distance from the heel to the toe of the face is greater than or equal to two thirds of the distance from the face to the back of the head;
                    the distance from the heel to the toe of the face is greater than or equal to half of the distance from the heel to the toe of the head; and
                    the distance from the sole to the top of the head, including any permitted features, is less than or equal to 2.5 inches (63.5 mm).
                  
 
              
            
          
          The following illustrations demonstrate the dimensional specifications for putters:
          
             
          The Rule goes on to describe how these measurements should be made for traditionally shaped heads and that for unusually shaped heads, the heel-to-toe measurement may be made at the face. Given the dimensional restrictions listed above, which help to control the size and shape of a putter head, the clause regarding unusually shaped heads is now rarely, if ever, applied.
          It is important to note that appendages are not permitted if they are for the purpose of meeting the dimensional specifications above.
          
            c. Spring Effect and Dynamic Properties 
          Effective January 1, 2008, the USGA re-worded and re-positioned the spring effect clause previously found under Rule 5a, Appendix II to this section of the Rules. Among other things, the language codified the underlying principles of several decisions made by the USGA over the past several years regarding spring design features. Rule 4c, Appendix II now states:
          
            
              
                
                  The design, material and/or construction of, or any treatment to, the clubhead (which includes the club face) must not:
                  (i) have the effect of a spring which exceeds the limit set forth in the Pendulum Test Protocol on file with the USGA, or
                  (ii) incorporate features or technology, including, but not limited to separate springs or spring features, that have the intent of, or the effect of, unduly influencing the clubhead's spring effect, or
                  (iii) unduly influence the movement of the ball.
                  Note: (i) above does not apply to putters.
                
              
            
          
          Because "spring effect" is purely a performance-related limit which cannot be easily measured in the field without specialized equipment and cannot be assessed through visual inspection of the clubhead, the USGA compiles and maintains a List of Conforming Driver Heads. The List is updated on a weekly basis and can be accessed through the USGA's Web site (www.usga.org). Additionally, features in the clubhead design that are intended to or have the effect of unduly influencing the clubhead's spring effect are not permitted. The USGA has adopted an interim test method to assist in streamlining evaluation of these types of designs and, as a result, if the spring effect of the clubhead, measured at any point on the face, does not exceed the limit set forth in the Pendulum Test Protocol on file, the clubhead would likely conform to this provision.
          For competitions involving expert players, the USGA recommends that the Committee in charge of the competition adopt the List of Conforming Driver Heads as a Condition of Competition (See Appendix I, Part C, Section 1a). The Condition requires that any driver a player carries must have a clubhead, identified by model and loft, that is named on the current List of Conforming Driver Heads issued by the USGA. It is important to note that a driver with a clubhead manufactured prior to 1999 is exempt from the requirement of the condition.
          While this Condition is not recommended for use by other competition committees, the Rules regarding club conformance, including spring effect, apply to all rounds conducted under USGA Rules of Golf, including those rounds played for the purpose of posting a handicap score.
          Finally, if a manufacturer makes claims of spring-like features or that a clubhead, other than a putter, exceeds the Pendulum Test limit, or if there is strong evidence to suggest that the club, in fact, exceeds the limit, then the club will be considered non-conforming to this Rule.
          
          
            d. Striking Faces 
          Appendix II, 4d states that:
          
            
              
                
                  The clubhead must only have one striking face, except that a putter may have two such faces if their characteristics are the same, and they are opposite each other.
                
              
            
          
          The exception for putters was introduced in order to accommodate traditional blade‑type putters.
          
            Determining whether a surface constitutes a second (or third) striking face is often a matter of opinion, However, in general, a surface should be considered an additional striking face if: 
          
            
              the area is flat and it is clearly designed to be used for striking the ball, or
              it is opposite the intended face and consists of a flat surface of a different loft and/or material, or
              it is a flat surface on the toe and/or heel of a cylindrical, rectangular or square head design which could effectively be used to strike the ball, or
              it could otherwise effectively be used to strike the ball.
            
          
          All three of the putters illustrated in Figure 35 would be ruled non‑conforming.
          
             
          The addition of lead tape to the back face of a putter with two conforming striking faces would not be contrary to the Rules. Additionally, cosmetic/decorative markings on one of two permissible surfaces, that do not affect performance, will not usually create a different striking face.
          
             
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14620</url>
      <title>Club Face</title>
      <body>
  
     
  
    
      
        
          
            5. Club Face 
          
          
            a. General 
          Appendix II, 5a states that:
          
            
              
                
                  The face of the club must be hard and rigid and must not impart significantly more or less spin to the ball than a standard steel face (some exceptions may be made for putters). Except for such markings listed below, the club face must be smooth and must not have any degree of concavity.
                
              
            
          
          If claims of excessive spin are made by the manufacturer, or if there is strong supporting evidence of excessive spin, then the club could be deemed to be non-conforming.
          The "hardness" rule is particularly relevant to putters, many of which have urethane or other "soft" material inserted into the face.
          
            The measure for "hardness" is made using a durometer. A putter face must have a hardness of no less than 85 on a Shore A scale durometer. A simple measure of hardness "in the field" would be to use a fingernail. If pressing a fingernail leaves a significant imprint in the face of a club, please consult the USGA and offer a Duration of Competition or Duration of Round ruling. The face of a wood or iron club must be substantially harder than a putter face, i.e., no less than 75 on a Shore D scale. 
          In the field, "rigidity" is interpreted to mean that the face should not have any visible signs of movement or flex when manual pressure is exerted.
          When an insert is incorporated into the club face, it should be flush with the rest of the face so that the face is still considered smooth and not concave. While we interpret concavity in this provision strictly, we also recognize that, due to manufacturing tolerances, it is difficult for every insert to be exactly flush with the rest of the face. As a result, we allow an insert to protrude by as much as 0.006 inches (0.15 mm) or be sunken by as much as 0.004 inches (0.1 mm). 
          
          
            b. Impact Area Roughness and Material 
          Appendix II, 5b states that:
          
            
              
                
                  Except for markings specified in the following paragraphs, the surface roughness within the area where impact is intended (the "impact area") must not exceed that of decorative sandblasting, or of fine milling. The whole of the impact area must be of the same material (exceptions may be made for clubheads made of wood).
                
              
            
          
          
            (i) Definition of ‘Impact Area' 
          
            Irons 
          The impact area for irons is that part of the club where a face treatment has been applied (e.g., grooves, sandblasting, etc.) or the central strip down the middle of the club face having a width of 1.68 inches (42.67 mm), whichever is greater.
          
            Woods 
          The impact area on driving clubs and fairway woods is defined as the central strip down the middle of the club face having a width of 1.68 inches (42.67 mm).
          
            Note: Grooves and/or punch marks traditionally used to mark the impact area, or any groove which encroaches into the heel or toe portions of the impact area by less than 0.25 inches (6.35 mm) do not have to meet the specifications detailed in Supplement C. However, such markings must not be designed to unduly influence, or have the effect of unduly influencing, the movement of the ball. 
          
            For clubs with inserts in the face, the boundary of the impact area is defined by the boundary of the insert, as long as any markings outside the boundary do not encroach the impact area by more than 0.25 inches (6.35 mm) and/or are not designed to influence the movement of the ball. Moreover, the insert itself must extend to at least 0.84 inches (21.34 mm) on either side of the center line of the face and to within at least 0.2 inches (5.08 mm) of the top line and leading edge of the face. 
          
             
          Please note that the above definitions of impact area only apply to new models of clubs manufactured on or after January 1, 2010. For clubs available prior to January 1, 2010, please refer to Supplement A (page 52 of this Guide).
          
            (ii) Impact Area Roughness 
          When dealing with the surface roughness of a club face (not including putters, see Design of Clubs, Section 5f), the claims made by the manufacturer must be taken into account - especially if there is a claim that the roughness of the face influences the movement of the ball. In the absence of such claims, the ruling would be made purely on the amount of roughness in the impact area. Sandblasting or other treatments of roughness greater than 180 micro inches are not permitted. In addition, for milling, the crest to trough depth must not exceed 0.001 inches (0.025 mm). A reasonable tolerance is allowed for both of these measurements. Non-conforming sandblasting or milling usually feels rough to the touch.
          
            (iii) Impact Area Material 
          The requirement that the whole of the "impact area" must be of the same material does not apply to clubs made of wood or putters (see Design of Clubs, Section 5f). The reason why it does not apply to wooden headed clubs is to allow the continued use of wooden clubs which have plastic inserts and brass screws in the center of the face. This design was commonly used in persimmon woods, which may still be in use. However, a club face or insert made of a composite material would be considered to be of a single material, and therefore would not be contrary to this rule.
          
            Metal wood club faces which have inserts of different material, not trapezoidal in shape, may be permitted if the height of the insert meets the definition of "impact area" and the width of the insert is the same as the height in at least one point. However, in order to preserve the intent of the "same material" Rule, clubs which have unusually shaped inserts of different material (i.e., other than circular, oval, square or rectangular) are not normally permitted. 
          
            If an insert of different material is permitted under the above guideline, the insert would be considered the "impact area" for that club. Therefore, any markings outside that area need not conform to the specifications provided in Appendix II, 5c. However, such markings must not be designed to unduly influence the movement of the ball. 
          
          
            
              c. Impact Area Markings
            
             
          Appendix II, 5c provides the specifications for impact area grooves and punch marks.
          
            
              
                
                  
                    If a club has grooves and/or punch marks in the impact area they must meet the following specifications:
                     
                  
                    (i) Grooves
                     
                  
                    Grooves must be straight and parallel.
                    Grooves must have a plain*, symmetrical cross-section and have sides which do not converge (see Figure XI).
                  
 
              
            
          
          
             
          
            
              
                
                  
                    The width, spacing and cross-section of the grooves must be consistent throughout the impact area.
                    The width (W) of each groove must not exceed 0.035 inches (0.9 mm), using the 30 degree method of measurement on file with the USGA.
                    The distance between edges of adjacent grooves (S) must not be less than three times the width of the grooves, and not less than 0.075 inches (1.905 mm).
                    The depth of each groove must not exceed 0.020 inches (0.508 mm).
                    *For clubs other than driving clubs, the cross-sectional area (A) of a groove divided by the groove pitch (W+S) must not exceed 0.0030 square inches per inch (0.0762 mm2/mm) (see Figure XII).
                  
 
              
            
          
          
             
          
            
              
                
                  
                    Grooves must not have sharp edges or raised lips.
                    *For clubs whose loft angle is greater than or equal to 25 degrees, groove edges must have an effective radius which is not less than 0.010 inches (0.254 mm) when measured as shown in Fig. XIII, and not greater than 0.020 inches (0.508 mm). Deviations in effective radius within 0.001 inches (0.0254 mm) are permissible.
                  
 
              
            
          
          
             
          
            
              
                
                  
                    (ii) Punch Marks
                     
                  
                    The maximum dimension of any punch mark must not exceed 0.075 inches (1.905 mm).
                    The distance between adjacent punch marks (or between punch marks and grooves) must not be less than 0.168 inches (4.27 mm), measured center to center.
                    The depth of any punch mark must not exceed 0.040 inches (1.02 mm).
                    *For clubs whose loft angle is greater than or equal to 25 degrees, punch mark edges must have an effective radius which is not less than 0.010 inches (0.254 mm) when measured as shown in Fig. XIII, and not greater than 0.020 inches (0.508 mm). Deviations in effective radius within 0.001 inches (0.0254 mm) are permissible.
                  
                  
                    Note 1: The groove and punch mark specifications above marked with an asterisk (*) apply only to new models of clubs manufactured on or after January 1, 2010 and any club where the face markings have been purposely altered, for example, by re-grooving. For further information on the status of clubs available before January 1, 2010, please refer to the Informational Club Database at www.usga.org.
                     
                  
                    Note 2: The Committee may require, in the conditions of competition, that the clubs the player carries must conform to the groove and punch mark specifications above marked with an asterisk (*). This condition is recommended only for competitions involving the highest level of expert player. For further information, refer to Decision 4-1/1 in "Decisions on the Rules of Golf.".
                    
                     
                
              
            
          
          
            The USGA has adopted this condition for the U.S. Open, U.S. Women's Open, and the U.S. Senior Open Championships conducted after January 1, 2010. By January 1, 2014, the USGA will adopt this condition for all other USGA Championships, as such championships involve expert players.
             
          
            For competitions conducted after January 1, 2014, the USGA does not recommend adoption of this Condition of Competition unless the competition involves professional-level players and/or players at the highest levels of amateur golf.
             
          
            If the Committee does not adopt the Condition of Competition, clubs available prior to January 1, 2010, which conformed to the 2008-2009 Rules of Golf may continue to be used in all rounds conducted under the Rules of Golf until at least 2024.
             
          
            A field test has been developed in order to assist golfers and Officials involved in elite level professional golf in determining the status of clubs available prior to January 1, 2010. Where access to a field test is not available, the USGA has also compiled and published an informational database of irons, fairway woods with lofts of 25 degrees or higher, and hybrids with lofts of 25 degrees or higher, submitted to the USGA and/or The R&amp;amp;A prior to Jan. 1, 2010 and evaluated to determine whether they meet the New Groove Rules. Unlike the List of Conforming Driver Heads, the Database is to be used for reference purposes only. The Database is not to be used in any manner stipulating that clubs must be included in the Database in order to be carried when the Condition of Competition is in effect.
             
          NOTE: The specifications for grooves and punch marks on clubs available before January 1, 2010, are set out in Supplement A along with a complete guide as to the procedure for measuring width, depth and separation when in the field. Additionally, clubs where the face markings have been purposely altered, for example, by re-grooving, must conform to the current groove and punch mark specifications. However, clubs which have only been refurbished back to their original state (e.g., through light sandblasting) may still be eligible for the grace period extended to pre-2010 models.
          
            
              (iii) Groove/Punch Mark Combinations
            
             
          
            If punch marks are used in combination with grooves, the following guidelines apply:
             
             
          
            
              Iron Clubs
            
             
          
            
              Small punch marks which are in line with a conforming groove, and which would be totally contained within a continuation of the groove, do not have to meet the punch mark to groove specifications. However, if the diameter of such punch marks exceeds the width of the groove, then they must meet the specifications.
              
                 
              When measuring the center to center distance between a punch mark and the end of an in-line groove, the center of the groove is deemed to be half a groove width from the end edge of the groove.
            
          
          
             
          
            
              Metal Wood Clubs
            
             
          
            Provided the following three conditions are satisfied, the preceding interpretation of the specifications for punch marks in line with a groove may also be granted for metal woods, even if the punch marks would not be totally contained by the continuation of the groove: 
          
            
              There must be no more than three in-line punch marks in the part of the groove that is missing (i.e., in the gap between the ends of the partial grooves);
              The combined area of all of the in-line punch marks in any one such gap must not exceed the area of the missing groove; and
              The separation of the in-line punch marks from adjacent parallel grooves - measured from center to center - must be at least four times the width of the groove.
            
          
          
            The following diagram illustrates each of the above conditions:
             
          
             
          
            
            
              d. Decorative Markings
            
             
          
            
              
                
                  
                    The center of the impact area may be indicated by a design within the boundary of a square whose sides are 0.375 inches (9.53 mm) in length. Such a design must not unduly influence the movement of the ball. Decorative markings are permitted outside the impact area.
                     
                
              
            
          
          
            The reason for this rule is to permit small, decorative logos in the center of the face or at the side of the "impact area." Non-conforming markings or logos that marginally encroach on the impact area may be permitted, (i.e., by less than .25 inches (6.35 mm)). However, markings outside the ‘impact area' which are designed to unduly influence, or have the effect of unduly influencing the movement of the ball would be contrary to this rule.
             
          
             
          
          
            
              e. Non-metallic Club Face Markings
            
             
          
            The specifications regarding grooves, punch marks and decorative markings that are applicable to metal faces, or faces made from similarly hard materials, do not apply to faces made from other materials and whose loft angle is 24 degrees or less. However, any markings which could influence the movement of the ball are not permitted on such clubs.
             
          
          
            
              f. Putter Face
            
             
          
            The specifications in Appendix II, 5, with regard to roughness, material and markings in the impact area, do not apply to putters. However, any grooves or other permissible markings on a putter face must not have sharp edges or raised lips.
             
          
            Additionally, if a groove or the grooves on the face of a putter exceed 0.035 inches in width and 0.020 inches in depth, the following guidelines apply: 
          
            
              The width may not exceed 0.06 inches.
              The width to spacing ratio must be no less than 1:1.
              The depth must be less than the width, and may not exceed 0.04 inches.
            
          
          Supplement A includes a complete guide regarding the procedure for measuring groove width, depth and separation when in the field.
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14610</url>
      <title>Rule 5 - The Golf Ball</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
    Rule 5 - The Golf Ball
  
  
  
  
    
      
        
          
            
              General
            
            
          
          
            Rule 5-1 provides that the ball that a player uses must conform to the Rules and that the use of a ball which does not conform to the Rules will result in disqualification. However, the player would have to play a stroke with a non-conforming ball in order for the disqualification penalty to apply (see also Decision 5-1/3 in "Decisions on the Rules of Golf").
          
          
            
              The List of Conforming Golf Balls
            
            
          
          
            Manufacturers may submit balls to the United States Golf Association and The R&amp;amp;A for testing. Twenty-four samples of each ball type (model) must be submitted to obtain a conformance ruling. If the samples conform to the Rules, they are entered onto the List of Conforming Golf Balls, which is updated on a monthly basis. The current list can be found on the USGA's Web site at www.usga.org. Full details of the golf ball submission procedure can be obtained from the USGA.
            
          
          
            Ball types remain on the List for one year. However, random tests are carried out by the USGA and The R&amp;amp;A on selected balls to ensure that the ball characteristics remain the same. If a conformance issue is identified during random testing, the ball may be removed from the List.
            
          
          
            Normally, only the Committees in charge of competitions involving expert players (at the state, regional and national level for amateurs, or at professional events) introduce a Condition of Competition requiring a player to use a ball included on the List of Conforming Golf Balls, the penalty for breach of the Condition being disqualification. However, if this Condition is not in place, it is assumed that a ball used by a player conforms unless there is strong evidence to the contrary (e.g., a player used a 1.62 inch diameter golf ball).
            
          
          
            
              Foreign Material (Rule 5-2)
            
            
          
          
            As with the club, the most important question to ask if confronted with a ball which has had something applied to it by the player is "why did the player apply it?" If the purpose of the application is to influence the movement of the ball, it would be prohibited.
            
          
          
            Markings applied to the ball by the player (e.g., using a felt-tip pen) are not contrary to this Rule. Rules 6 5 and 12 2 encourage the player to put an identification mark on his ball to help ensure that he plays his own ball throughout the round. There are no regulations to limit what or how many markings can be applied to the ball by the player, provided its original markings can be discerned.
            
          
          
             
          
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14611</url>
      <title>Appendix III - The Ball</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
  
    
      
        
          
            
              Appendix III - The Ball
            
          
          
             
          
          
            
              Introduction
            
            
          
          
            Appendix III is divided into the following six categories:
            
          
          
            General
            Weight
            Size
            Spherical Symmetry
            Initial Velocity
            Overall Distance Standard
          
          
            Prior to 2008, the Rules on the golf ball were precise and numerical in comparison to the more descriptive rules relating to clubs. In 2008, the USGA added general language to the Rules on golf balls to ensure that any new technology which may be developed in the future which might circumvent the intent of the Rules, while generally covered in the preamble to Appendices II and III, was also directly addressed in Appendix III. Other than this general provision, all of the specifications listed below are tested and checked under laboratory conditions. These specifications are discussed briefly below. However, the official test protocols are available on the USGA's Web site.
          
          
            
              1. General
            
            
          
          
            
              
                
                  
                    The ball must not be substantially different from the traditional and customary form and make. The material and construction of the ball must not be contrary to the purpose and intent of the Rules.
                    
                  
                
              
            
          
          
            Along with the specifications listed below, the USGA conducts additional testing and inspections to identify golf balls with unusual material, construction and/or performance characteristics which may be considered substantially different from the traditional and customary form and make and/or contrary to the purpose and intent of the Rules.
            
          
          
            
              2. Weight
            
            
          
          
            Appendix III, 2 states that a ball must not weigh more than 1.620 ounces avoirdupois (45.93 gm). This is one of the simpler tests because all that is required is an accurate scale. There is no minimum weight, thus a ball can be as light as the manufacturer desires.
            
          
          
            
              3. Size
            
            
          
          
            The ball must have a diameter of not less than 1.680 inches (42.67 mm). The instrument used to measure size is a metal ring gauge. It is important to note that there is no maximum size, the ball can be as large as desired provided it conforms to all other standards.
            
          
          
            
              4. Spherical Symmetry
            
            
          
          
            The intent of this rule is simply to ensure that a ball is designed and manufactured to behave symmetrically.
            
          
          
            
              5. Initial Velocity
            
            
          
          
            There is a formal test procedure carried out on equipment approved by the USGA to check that golf balls meet the Initial Velocity specification. The intent of this Rule is to limit the speed of the ball off the clubface.
            
          
          
            
              6. Overall Distance Standard
            
            
          
          This Rule was introduced in 1976 in order to restrict the overall distance (carry and roll) that a ball can travel under specific conditions. This test protocol is continuously reviewed to ensure that it reflects the game as played with modern equipment.
        
      
    
  
   
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14612</url>
      <title>Supplement A</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
    
  
  
    
      
        
          
            Supplement A
          
          
            
              Guidance on How to Measure Grooves on Club Faces for Conformance to the 2008-2009 Rules of Golf - In The Field 
            
            
          
          
            
              Introduction
            
            
          
          The following pages give guidance on how to measure grooves on club faces for width and separation, using the "Ink and Scratch" method, and depth. They concentrate solely on the Rules which apply to the grooves on iron and wood clubs available prior to January 1, 2010, but, if necessary, the same procedures and equipment can be used to measure grooves on a putter face (see Design of Clubs, Section 5f).
          
            For those officials who have not previously carried out these measurements, we recommend setting aside time, a day or more prior to the tournament, for groove checking if required, rather than performing checks on the first day. It only takes a few minutes to measure the grooves on a club, but it is important not to be rushed. We also recommend practice-measuring on at least six club faces - preferably more - before performing it in the field.
            
          
          
            A one-page summary of the procedure for measuring the width and separation of the grooves on iron and wood clubs is attached, which, when used in conjunction with the specially designed results sheet, may give sufficient instruction, once the user has gained some experience in measuring grooves. An abbreviated form of the test, appropriate for clubs which comfortably meet the groove specifications, is also outlined.
            
          
          
            
              Groove Width and Separation
            
            
          
          
            In order to carry out the "Ink and Scratch" method of measuring grooves, the following equipment is required:
            
          
          
            A thick black marker pen (e.g., a Sharpie®)
            A carbide wedge ‘Marking Tool' (see Fig. 2)
            A magnifier
            A steel ruler
            An alcohol wipe (to clean the club face)
          
          
            The carbide tool and magnifier are available from the USGA at a reasonable cost.
            
          
          
            
              How to Ink and Mark the Grooves
            
            
          
          
            
              
            
            
              1. 
            
            
              
            
            Make sure that the club face and grooves are clean. Also check that the tungsten carbide "wedge" in the marking tool is properly square to the axis of the tool and securely fixed. If not, adjust with the Allen key provided.
            
          
          
            
              
            
            
              2. 
            
            Use the marker pen to coat an approximately 0.25 to 0.5 inch width of the edges of five grooves (and the nearby part of the flat area between them), making sure that the ink gets down into the grooves. The inked pattern thus formed should lie in a line running from the sole to top edge of the fifth groove. For new clubs, do this about 0.5 inches to one side of the center of the face (see Fig. 1 below). For used clubs, do it near the toe, but not at the very end of the grooves (but see also Supplement A, Paragraph 13).
            
          
          
            
          
          
            3. When the ink is dry, take the marking tool, hold it like a pencil at about 45 degrees to the club face and insert the pointed corner of its tip into one of the blackened grooves (See Fig. 2). Using firm but not too heavy pressure, pull the tool along the groove for about 0.25 inches. Two narrow bright lines of exposed metal should now be visible, one on each side of the groove denoting the position of the edges of the grooves. (See Fig. 3).
          Do the same for all five blackened grooves. 
          
            
          
          
            
              How to Use the Magnifier
            
            
          
          
            
              4. 
            
            The magnifier comes with two scales, a short scale with a line pre-measured at 0.035 inches (width scale) and a long scale (separation scale).
            
          
          
            
              5. 
            
            
              
            
            Rest the clubhead on a table or other surface, so that the club face is horizontal. You may find it helps to rest the club's shaft on your shoulder or on some raised object, in order to leave both hands free to adjust the magnifier. Since good light is needed, it is helpful, indoors, to place a reading lamp close to the clubhead, preferably shining along the direction of the grooves on the club face. Make sure you hold the magnifier in such a way that your fingers do not obscure the light.
            
          
          
            
              6. 
            
            Place the magnifier on the club face and look through it. By turning the knurled ring on the eyepiece, you should be able to bring into sharp focus both the scale and surface features on the club face. You should also be able to see clearly the bright edges you have scraped on the grooves against the black background.
            
          
          Notice that the magnifier scale is in thousandths of inches and is marked at intervals of 0.005 inches. (See Fig. 4).
          
            
          
          
            
          
          
            
              Measuring the Grooves
            
            
          
          
            
              7. 
            Use the magnifier to measure the width (W) of the five grooves whose edges have been marked by the tool. This may be done by lining up the width scale along the left edge of each groove (i.e., along the left of the bright line scratched by the tool) and reading off the position of the other edge on the portion of the magnifier scale (i.e., along the left of the bright line scratched by the tool). For best results, the scratched line should be about 0.005 inches wide. If it is appreciably wider than 0.005 inches, then too much pressure has been applied in using the marking tool. In that case, abandon that particular part of the groove and do a repeat "ink and scratch" slightly to one side.
          Record all five groove widths. Often they will be the same, or differ by only .0025 inches. Please refer to Supplement B of this Guide.
          
            8. Determine the groove separation (D) (See Fig. 5).
          
            
          
          Using the magnifier, measure the distance from one edge of groove 1 to the corresponding edge of groove 5 (i.e., over four land areas). The best way to do this is to position the separation scale on the left edge of groove 1 and read off the distance on the left edge of groove 5 (record as D on the worksheet).
          Finally, determine the land area between the grooves (the distance between edges of adjacent grooves) by lining up the long magnifier along the right edge of one groove and the left edge of the next and reading off the position of the left edge of the groove.
          
            Errors and Uncertainty in Measuring
          
          
            
              9. 
            With a little practice you can measure the groove width with as little as 0.0025 inch tolerance (i.e., it could be wrong by at most 0.0025 inches). In tests for conformity, the manufacturer is given the benefit of all of the uncertainty.
          
            
              How to Determine Whether Grooves Conform to Pre-2010 Groove Requirements
            
            
          
          Note: For most levels of play, clubs available prior to January 1, 2010 that conform to the pre-2010 requirements may continue to be used in rounds played under USGA Rules of Golf until at least 2024.
          
            
              Definition of Impact Area for Clubs Available Prior to January 1, 2010 
            
            
          
          
            For iron clubs, the "impact area" is deemed to be that part of the face which lies within 0.80 inches (20 mm) on either side of the vertical center line of the face.
          
          
            For metal wood clubs, the shape of the impact area is generally based on the traditional inserts used in persimmon-type wood clubs. The shape and dimensions of this area can best be illustrated as follows:
          
          
            The height (h) of the trapezoid is used to fix the horizontal dimensions - namely "1/2h" at the top and "h" at the base. This ensures that all impact areas are similar (see Fig. 6).
          
          
            
          
          
            10. The pre-2010 specifications for grooves that may be applied to the club face provide:
          
            
              
                
                  
                    Grooves must not have sharp edges or raised lips (test on file).
                    Grooves must be straight and parallel.
                    Grooves must have a symmetrical cross-section and have sides which do not converge.
                    The width, spacing and cross-section of the grooves must be consistent throughout the impact area.
                    Any rounding of groove edges shall be in the form of a radius which does not exceed 0.020 inches (0.508 mm).
                    The width of the grooves shall not exceed 0.035 inches (0.9 mm), using the 30 degree method of measurement on file with the USGA.
                    The distance between edges of adjacent grooves must not be less than three times the width of a groove, and not less than 0.075 inches (1.905 mm).
                  
                
              
            
          
          
            The specifications can be further explained as follows:
            
          
          (i) The width must not exceed 0.035 inches (0.9 mm): We currently interpret "width" as the average width and, therefore, the measured grooves do not conform if the average width of grooves 1 through 5 is greater than 0.035 inches.
          However, if any one groove is greater than the maximum allowable plus 0.002 inches, the club does not conform.
          (ii) The distance between edges of adjacent grooves must be not less than three times the width of a groove. Using the average of the five groove widths, multiply it by three and compare it to your measurements of land area.
          
            
              
            
            (iii) 
            The distance between edges of adjacent grooves must not be less than 0.075
             inches
             (1.9 mm): Again, using the average of the five groove widths, compare it to your measurements of land area (applies if the average groove width &amp;lt; 0.025
             inches
            ).
            
          
          
            
              
            
            (iv) 
            Groove widths must be consistent: We interpret this to mean that the difference in width between the second widest and the second narrowest groove must not exceed 0.005
             inches
            .
            
          
          
            
              11. 
            
            
              
            
            We recognize that groove measurements made, as these are, at one point along the length of the grooves, are sensitive to small manufacturing errors. Therefore, if a club fails on one of the above criteria, it should not immediately be declared non-conforming; rather the whole measuring procedure should be repeated at a slightly different part of the face (perhaps 0.40 inches to the other side of the center of a club face from the first set). For a club to be declared non-conforming in the field, it must fail to meet the same specification on both sets of measurements. In the case of a single overwidth groove (Wmax), the same groove must be overwidth on both measurements.
            
          
          
            
              Irregular or Unusual Grooves
            
            
          
          
            
              12. 
            
            
              
            
            For grooves with markedly varying separation (see Fig. 7), the same measuring technique applies. Difficult cases should be submitted to the USGA for a ruling.
            
          
          
            
          
          
            
              13. 
            
            
              
            
            For used clubs with worn grooves, the width measurements must be made on grooves which are not worn. These can nearly always be found near the toe of the club, or high on the face. Avoid the extreme end of the grooves since the width sometimes varies there. If it is not possible to find five unworn grooves, measure as many as possible and make the necessary modifications to the calculation of average width.
            
          
          If the grooves on a used club have been deliberately altered by filing or the use of a groove scoring tool, then the club should be treated as though it were new and the grooves measured near the center of the face (see Rule 4-1b).
          
            
              14. 
            
            
              
            
            Very occasionally grooves will be found which are either very shallow, or have sides which make an angle of less than 30 degrees to the horizontal. In these circumstances the marking tool will not work properly and the club should be submitted to the USGA for a ruling, although if the grooves clearly conform, it may be possible to give a conforming ruling in the field.
            
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14613</url>
      <title>Summary of Groove Measuring Procedure</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
  
    
      
        
          
            
              SUMMARY OF GROOVE MEASURING PROCEDURE
            
            
          
          
            
          
          
            (The bracketed numbers refer to the corresponding paragraphs in Supplement A - "Guidance on How to Measure Grooves on Club Faces for Conformance to the 2008-2009 Rules of Golf - In The Field")
            
          
          
            Clean club face [1]; ink the edges of five grooves in a 0.5 inch wide band [2].
            Check marking tool [1]; use it as described in full instructions [3] to scrape the edges of the inked grooves.
            Use the magnifier to measure the width of all five grooves, and record on the results sheet [4, 5, 6, 7].
            Measure the distance over five grooves to determine "D" [8].
            Measure the distance between the edges of the five grooves [8].
            Complete the worksheet in Supplement B of this Guide.
            Using quantities calculated on the worksheet, answer the questions near the bottom of the results sheet to determine whether the grooves conform [10, 11]. Manufacturers are advised to use actual widths in these calculations [12].
            Follow the steps on the results sheet to reach a decision on the club, repeating the measurement if necessary [11].
          
          
            
          
          
            * * *
            
          
          
            Note: Consult the full instructions for grooves with inconsistent spacing, or other unusual features [12, 13, 14].
            
          
          
            
          
          
            
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14614</url>
      <title>Abbreviated Procedure for Groove Measurement</title>
      <body>
  
  
    
  
  
    
      ABBREVIATED PROCEDURE FOR GROOVE MEASUREMENTS
    
    
  
  
     
  
  
    
      
        
          
            It may be quite acceptable, for an experienced user of the measuring equipment, to abbreviate the measuring procedure on clubs whose grooves clearly lie well within the specified dimensions.
            
          
          
            First, inspect the club face by eye, and check whether the grooves are:
            
          
          
            
                                      
            
            a)
            
                
            
            unevenly spaced
            
          
          
            
                                      
            
            b)
            
                
            
            of unequal width
            
          
          
            
                                      
            
            c)
            
                
            
            unusually wide
            
          
          
            
                                      
            
            d)
            
                
            
            unusually close together
            
          
          
            If any of these conditions apply, then the full measurement must be carried out.
            
          
          
            If none of these conditions apply, follow the procedure on the previous page.
            
          
          
             
          
          
            IF YOU HAVE ANY DOUBT, CARRY OUT THE FULL MEASUREMENT.
            
          
          
             
          
          
            
              Groove Depth
            
            
          
          
            The pre-2010 specifications go on to state:
            
          
          
            
              
                
                  
                    The depth of a groove must not exceed 0.020 inches (0.508 mm).
                    
                  
                
              
            
          
          
            In order to help officials rule on groove depth in the field, a simple gauge has been developed which is available from the USGA at a reasonable cost.
            
          
          
            The gauge consists of a small rectangular block which has a raised, thin, protruding ridge. This ridge measures exactly 0.022 inches (0.559 mm) in depth, which offers a small tolerance suitable for measurements made in the field.
            
          
          
            
              Method of Use
            
            
          
          
            In order to judge the depth of a groove on a club, the block should be placed onto the face with the ridge running along the inside of the groove. The user should then apply pressure to the block, on both sides of the ridge, to see if the block will rock from side to side.
            
          
          If the block does noticeably rock, then the groove cannot be too deep. It means that the depth of the ridge is greater that the depth of the groove.
          
            If, on the other hand, the block lies flush with the face and cannot be rocked, it means that the groove is likely to be too deep.
            
          
          
            In both instances above, the gauge should be used on at least six grooves within the "impact area" of the face (or near the toe for club faces which are quite worn).
            
          
          
            The player should be advised not to use the club in a situation where at least three grooves appear to be too deep when using the gauge.
            
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-2147483902</url>
      <title>2008-2009 Punch Mark Specifications</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
  
    
      
        
          
            2008-2009 Punch Mark Specifications 
            
          
          
            The pre-2010 specifications for punch marks state:
          
          
            
              (ii) Punch Marks
            
          
          
            
              
                
                  
                    The area of any such mark must not exceed 0.0044 square inches (2.84 sq.mm).
                    The distance between adjacent punch marks (or between punch marks and grooves) must not be less than 0.168 inches (4.27 mm) measured from center to center.
                    The depth of a punch mark must not exceed 0.040 inches (1.02 mm).
                    Punch marks must not have sharp edges or raised lips (test on file).
                  
                
              
            
          
          
            Punch marks are almost always circular in shape, and therefore the area of the punch mark can be determined using the calculation πr2 (where π =~3.142). The radius of the punch mark (circle) can be measured using the same magnifier that is used for measuring grooves (see Supplement A), as can the separation of two punch marks - measured center to center. The depth gauge used for measuring groove depths would not be suitable for measuring the depth of a punch mark. This measurement would require the use of a depth probe. While the depth of a punch mark is limited to 0.040 inches (1.02 mm) within the Rules, it is highly unlikely that this measurement would be requested in the field.
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-14615</url>
      <title>Supplement B</title>
      <body>
  
    Supplement B 
  
  
    GROOVE MEASUREMENT DATA SHEET
    
    (Applies to Pre-2010 Groove Requirements)
  
  
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
    
      
        CLUB = __________ 
    
      
    
    
      DATE = __________
    
      
    
    
      
        LINE
      
    
  
  
  
    
      
        
          
          1) Distance from groove 1 to groove 5
        
         
        
          D
        
        
          =
        
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
        
          2) Maximum allowable groove width (D/16)
        
        =
        W max allow
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
        3) W max allow + 0.002
        =
        Upper limit
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
        4) W max allow - 0.002
        =
        Lower limit
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
        5) Individual groove measurements:
         
        W1
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
         
         
        W2
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
         
         
        W3
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
         
         
        W4
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
         
         
        W5
        =
        
          ______ 
          
        
      
      
         
         
         
         
         
      
      
         
         
         
         
         
      
    
  
  
    
      
        
          6) If any width W1 - W5 is greater than "W max allow +0.002 inches (Upper limit from line 3 above) then the club DOES NOT conform. 
          7) If all widths are less than "W max allow -0.002 inches (Lower limit from line 4 above) the club conforms. 
          8) If any groove width is between the Upper and lower limits, the club should be submitted to the USGA for a precise laboratory measurement and the player should be given a Duration of Competition Answer if the club has not been previously examined by the USGA.
          9) The rule states that the minimum distance between grooves (land area) shall not be less than .075 inches and not less than three times the width of the groove. If the land area between any two grooves is less than .073 inches the club does not conform. If the distance is greater than .077 inches the club conforms to this part of the specification. If the distance is between .073 inches and .077 inches, submit the club to the USGA for a precise measurement. 
        
      
    
  
  
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-2147483650</url>
      <title>Supplement C</title>
      <body>
  
    
      Supplement C
     
  
     
  
    
      
        
          
            
              Club Face Markings Effective From January 1, 2010 - Addendum
            
          
          
            New Specifications and Interpretation
          
          Effective January 1, 2010, the Rules on club face markings include the following three additional specifications for clubs other than driving clubs and putters:The total cross-sectional area of a groove divided by the pitch (width plus separation) will be limited to 0.0030 square inches per inch (0.0762 mm2/mm);Groove edge sharpness will be required to be substantially in the form of a round having an effective minimum radius of 0.010 inches (0.254 mm). This limit only applies to clubs with lofts of 25 degrees and above.Grooves will be required to be plain.
          As previously noted in Section 5c, these new specifications apply only to new models of clubs manufactured on or after January 1, 2010 and competitions where the Groove and Punch Mark Condition of Competition is in effect.
          
            
              Interpretation of "Substantially in the Form of a Round" and "Plain"
            
             
          
            
              (I) Rounding
            
             
          
            Groove edge requirements apply only to clubs with lofts of 25 degrees and higher.
             
          
            The groove starts where there is a significant departure from the plane of the face ("land") and this is joined to the wall of the groove via the edge. The wall continues to the base of the groove.
             
          
            The edge must be substantially in the form of a round (having an effective radius of not less than 0.010", as determined by the two circles method, and not greater than 0.020"), which comprises an arc to which the groove wall and the land are tangential. As such, the ends of the "round" coincide with the ends of the edge - one end marking the joint to the land and one end marking the start of the groove wall. To further clarify, this means that groove edges must be a convex curve and must not include serrations, gear teeth or other similar features.
             
          
            The USGA reserves the right to define the extent of the groove edge. Edge configurations, including (but not limited to) chamfers, fillets, notches and other such features, do not conform to the rule because they are not in the form of a round. An allowance may be made for edge regions not strictly fulfilling this requirement as a result of production variations, but any such variations must be minimal and must not be part of the club's intended design.
             
          
            
              (II) Plain Groove
            
             
          
            The following geometry requirements apply to all clubs other than drivers and putters.
             
          
            (i) The wall of the groove must be substantially "plain" and "planar." This disallows features such as bends, indentations in or protrusions from the wall.
             
          
            (ii) The base of the groove must also be substantially "plain" and join the two opposing walls of the groove using a concave shape or a plane.
             
          
             
          Note: For clubs with lofts less than 25 degrees, where it is difficult to determine whether a groove violates either the edge requirement or the plain wall requirement, the groove will be deemed to meet the plain groove wall requirement. 
           
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
    <rule>
      <url>/rules/rules-and-decisions.html#!rule-2147483652</url>
      <title>Supplement D</title>
      <body>
  
    
  
  
    
      Supplement D
    
  
  
    
      
        
          
            
              Determining the Conformance Status of Grooves in the Impact Area Effective January 1, 2010
            
            
          
          
            The following algorithm will be used to determine the conformance of clubs to the new Rules on impact area markings, regardless of what method has been used to obtain the measurements.
            
            Within the following procedure, the inherent difficulty of manufacturing grooves has been taken into consideration.
            
            However, it should be noted that clubs must be designed and manufactured with the intent of conforming to the Rules.
            
          
          
            
              
                Note that for all dimensional limitations described below, each measurement will be based on a confidence level of at least 95% as determined by standard Gage R&amp;amp;R procedures. All measurements will include appropriate outlier controls to ensure that rulings are not based on spurious or anomalous data. Improvements to measurement techniques and, consequently, the associated measurement tolerances may be introduced at any time.
              
            
            
          
          
            
              (i) Groove Width
            
            
          
          
            If 50% or more of the measured groove widths exceed 0.035 inches (0.889 mm), then the club is non-conforming.
            If any single measured groove width exceeds 0.037 inches (0.940 mm), then the club is non-conforming. 

          
          
            
              (ii) Groove Depth
            
          
          
            If 50% or more of the measured groove depths exceed 0.020 inches (0.508 mm), then the club is non-conforming.
            If any single measured groove depth exceeds 0.022 inches (0.559 mm), then the club is non-conforming.
          
          
            
              (iii) Groove Separation
            
          
          
            If 50% or more of the measured groove separations are less than three times the maximum adjacent measured groove width, then the club is non-conforming.
            If any single measured groove separation is less than three times the maximum adjacent measured groove width minus 0.008 inches (0.203 mm), then the club is non-conforming.
            If 50% or more of the measured groove separations are less than 0.075 inches (1.905 mm), then the club is non-conforming.
            If any single measured groove separation is less than 0.073 inches (1.854 mm), then the club is non-conforming.
          
          
            
              (iv) Groove Consistency
            
            
          
          
            The range of measured groove widths cannot exceed 0.010 inches (0.254 mm).
            The range of measured groove depths cannot exceed 0.010 inches (0.254 mm).
          
          
            
              Inconsistencies in the groove width, spacing or cross-section for the purpose of unduly influencing the movement of the ball are not permitted, regardless of whether the above requirements are satisfied.
            
          
          
            
            
          
          
            
              (v) Area over Width Plus Separation
            
            
          
          
            If 50% or more of the measured values of A/(W+S) are greater than 0.0030 in2/in (0.0762 mm2/mm), then the club is non-conforming.
            If the measured value of A/(W+S) value for any single groove is greater than 0.0032 in2/in (0.0813 mm2/mm), then the club is non-conforming.
          
          
            
              (vi) Groove Edge Radius
            
            
          
          
            Rounding of groove and punch mark edges shall be in the form of a radius having an effective radius not less than 0.010 inches as determined by the two circles method described in Appendix C of the Test Protocol.
            
            The following two criteria are used for determining conformance:
            
          
          
            If 50% or more of the upper groove edges or 50% or more of the lower groove edges fail the two circles method subject to a 10 degree angular allowance, then the club is non-conforming.
            If any single groove edge protrudes more than 0.0003 inches (0.0076 mm) outside the outer circle (refer to Appendix C of the Test Protocol), then the club is non-conforming. 
          
          
            
              (vii) Punch Marks
            
            
          
          
            If 50% or more of the punch mark edges fail the two circles method subject to a 10 degree angular allowance, then the club is non-conforming.
            If any single punch mark edge protrudes more than 0.0003 inches (0.0076 mm) outside the outer circle (refer to Appendix C of the Test Protocol), then the club is non-conforming.
          
          
            Note: 
            
            For all clubs other than drivers and putters, the volume of punch marks in the impact area must not exceed the allowable area over width plus separation for an equivalent groove (i.e., 0.0030 in3/in2 per square inch of impact area covered by punch marks).
            
          
        
      
    
  
</body>
    </rule>
  </rules>
  <decisions />
</content>